Finding aid to the Carole De Saram papers SSC.MS.00794
Sophia Smith Collection
Carole De Saram papers
1970-2017
1970-1982
Sophia Smith Collection
De Saram, Carole
SSC.MS.00794
10.5 linear feet (8 record cartons, 1 oversize box, and 1 flat file folder)
110 Megabytes (76 files copied from one flash drive)
Carole De Saram was a feminist activist in the 1970s, working as President of New York City National Organization for Women (NOW) for women's equality in all fields. Her papers include documents, legal information, conference and protest information, and organizational information about the National Organization for Women, as well as photographs, correspondence, and personal documents of Carole De Saram.
Conditions Governing Access
This collection is open for use without restriction beyond the standard terms and conditions of Smith College Special Collections.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Donated by Carole De Saram in December 2017
Biographical / Historical
Carole De Saram was a feminist activist in the 1970s, working as President of New York City National Organization for Women (NOW) for women's equality in all fields.
Born February 27, 1939 in Queens, New York, De Saram began her career in computing, working on Wall Street at the American Stock Exchange. Inspired by a Wall Street Journal article on women striking for equality, De Saram attended the 1970 March for Equality, and continued working for NOW from that day on. Among her achievements were the woman-led stock exchange takeover, the creation of a women's bank and the Feminist Credit Union, disruption of the US presentation at the 1975 International Women's Conference in Mexico City to protest their choice of US representatives, and numerous incendiary demonstrations against sexist practices of New York City businesses. She became President of NOW NY in 1974, serving two terms, and rose through the ranks at Chemical Bank to become Assistant Vice President while pioneering computer projects with IBM. Written about in "Glamour," investigated by the FBI, and still working in activism in the 2010s, Carole De Saram left her mark on the feminist movement as a whole.
Scope and Contents
The Carole De Saram papers document her role agitating for credit for women in the 1970s and 1980s as part of NYC Now, as well as her participation in International Women's Year in Mexico City. The collection is largely clippings, although original records are interspersed throughout.
The collection includes documents, legal information (FOI requests and responses, lawsuit information, ERA legal proceedings), NOW national conference packets, and protest information, as well as organizational information (membership lists, board meeting notes and proceedings, various referenda) about the National Organization for Women. The collection also includes photographs, correspondence, digital photos and documents related to the Women's Movement compiled by Carole De Saram, and personal documents of Carole De Saram.
International Women's Year, 1975; Computer media; National Organization for Women--History--Sources; Equal rights amendments--United States--History--Sources; Feminism -- New York(State) -- New York -- History -- 20th century -- Sources; De Saram, Carole; De Saram, Carole
- National NOW newspapers and newsletters, including "Do It Now!", 1970-1980 (Box 1)
- National NOW Equal Rights Amendment actions, 1970-1978 (Box 1)
- National NOW Legal Defense & Education Fund, approximately 1975 (Box 1)
- NOW regional conference records, 1973-1976 (Box 1)
- NOW national conference records, 1973-1981 (Box 1)
- National NOW "Zap" actions, August 1974 (Box 1)
- National NOW Board records, including notes, correspondence, press releases, and member bios, 1973-1977 (Box 2)
- National NOW board split and walk out, 1974 (Box 2)
- Politics and elections, including women's campaigns and the inauguration of Jimmy Carter, 1974-1984 (Box 2)
  Scope and Contents
  Includes information on elections (both local and national) including the Jimmy Carter Presidential election and inauguration, information about women's participation in politics, NOW elections, NOW publications on which local or national politicans to endorse, and an NBC piece on the history of women's suffrage.
- Sex discrimination cases, including Congressional hearings, newspaper clippings, correspondence, and NOW Stockholder Action Task Force materials, 1973-1977 (Box 3)
  Includes research and evidence on various cases of gender discrimination, press articles, relevant New York State laws, a FOI request filed by de Saram and its responses, information from Congressional hearings on discrimination cases, and information on corporate stocks.
- NYNOW Freedom of Information request & responses, 1976-1977 (Box 3)
- New York NOW member information, July 26, 1976 (Box 9)
- Sexual Discrimination Cases, including legislation, action handbooks, events and conferences, 1973-1977 (Box 4)
- NYNOW FBI files, 1972-1979 (Box 4)
- NOW New York Chapter: newsletters, membership lists, political campaign materials, and chapter information, 1970-2003; 5 folders (Box 5)
- Equal Rights Amendment: newsletters, State campaign materials, anti-ERA literature, correspondence, and pamphlets, 1974-2004 (Box 6)
- Publications and Booklets, 1972-2009 (Box 6)
  Various publications on women's rights and the women's movement, including those from NOW, women's history archives, legal guides and reports, and pamphlets.
- International Women's Year Records: programming, participant biographies, pamphlets, and New York State meeting materials, 1975-1978 (Box 7)
- International Women's Year conference and Equal Rights Amendment posters, 1975; 4 items (Folder 1)
- Women's Institutions and Groups, including the Redstockings, the New York Feminist Credit Bureau, and the Veteran Feminists of America, 1968-1991 (Box 8)
- Carole De Saram personal papers: correspondence, photographs, and published articles, 1974-2017 (Box 8)
- "Women's Movement": presentation materials compiled electronically by Carole De Saram, approximately 1970-2007; 1 items (1 flash drive); 110 Megabytes (76 files copied from one flash drive) (Box 8)
  Primarily scanned photographs and documents. Topics include women's organizations (NOW, IWY), actions, and issues (ERA); conventions; letters, speaking engagements; and personal photographs.
  Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
  This file contains materials received from the donor in digital form that are not currently available online. Please consult with Special Collections staff to request access to this digital content.